<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Sam Shanny-Csik</title>
<link>https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.56</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:37:20 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>EDS 240 - Data Visualization &amp; Communication</title>
  <link>https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-240-data-viz/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="cell" data-layout-align="center">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-240-data-viz/horst-ggplot-masterpiece.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" style="width:50.0%" alt="A fuzzy monster in a beret and scarf, critiquing their own column graph on a canvas in front of them while other assistant monsters (also in berets) carry over boxes full of elements that can be used to customize a graph (like themes and geometric shapes). In the background is a wall with framed data visualizations. Stylized text reads 'ggplot2: build a data masterpiece.'"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="center-text">
<p><a href="https://eds-240-data-viz.github.io/" class="btn" target="_blank"><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> course website</a></p>
</div>
<!-- [ course catalog](https://bren.ucsb.edu/courses/eds-240){.btn target=_blank} -->
<p><br></p>
<section id="course-description" class="level1">
<h1>Course description</h1>
<p>Effectively communicating your work in a responsible, accessible and visually-pleasing way is often (if not, always) a central part of data science. This course will focus on the basic principles for effective communication through data visualization and using technical tools and workflows for creating and sharing data visualizations with diverse audiences.</p>
<p>By the end of this course, learners should be able to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Identify which types of visualizations are most appropriate for your data and your audience</li>
<li>Prepare (e.g.&nbsp;clean, explore, wrangle) data so that it’s appropriately formatted for building data visualizations</li>
<li>Build effective, responsible, accessible, and aesthetically-pleasing, visualizations using the R programming language, and specifically <code>{ggplot2}</code> + ggplot2 extension packages</li>
<li>Write code from scratch and read and adapt code written by others</li>
<li>Apply a DEI (Diversity, Equity &amp; Inclusion) lens to the process of designing data visualizations</li>
<li>Assess, critique, and provide constructive feedback on data visualizations</li>
</ul>
<!-- <br> -->
</section>
<section id="when-is-this-taught" class="level1">
<h1>When is this taught?</h1>
<p>EDS 240 is a <a href="https://bren.ucsb.edu/masters-programs/master-environmental-data-science/academics-meds/meds-courses">core course</a> of the <a href="https://bren.ucsb.edu/masters-programs/master-environmental-data-science/academics-meds">Master of Environmental Data Science</a> (MEDS) program, taught in Winter quarter each year (since the inaugural cohort, Winter 2022). I had so much fun redesigning and teaching it for the first time in Winter 2024, and I reflect on my experiences in my blog post, <a href="https://samanthacsik.github.io/posts/2024-04-02-data-viz-course/">BuiLding (and teaching) a graduate-level data science course</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>MEDS</category>
  <category>active-course</category>
  <guid>https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-240-data-viz/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:37:20 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-240-data-viz/EDS240-hex-smaller.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>EDS 296 - Intro to Shiny</title>
  <link>https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-296-shiny/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="cell" data-layout-align="center">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-296-shiny/shiny-hex.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" style="width:25.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="center-text">
<p><a href="https://ucsb-meds.github.io/EDS-296-Intro-to-Shiny/" class="btn" target="_blank"><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> course website</a></p>
</div>
<!-- [ course catalog](https://bren.ucsb.edu/courses/eds-296-1w){.btn target=_blank} -->
<p><br></p>
<section id="course-description" class="level1">
<h1>Course description</h1>
<p>These materials accompany the 2-unit, 2-day, hands-on coding course, <a href="https://bren.ucsb.edu/courses/eds-296-1w">EDS 296 - Intro to Shiny</a>, offered through the <a href="https://bren.ucsb.edu/">Bren School of Environmental Science &amp; Management</a>, in partnership with the <a href="https://www.nceas.ucsb.edu/">National Center for Ecological Analysis &amp; Synthesis</a>.</p>
<p>In this course, students learn how to build and deploy Shiny applications. The <a href="https://shiny.posit.co/"><code>{shiny}</code> package</a> provides a framework that allows R users to build interactive web applications and dashboards, and has become a popular tool for sharing data analyses and data-derived outputs with broad audiences. We cover the fundamentals of reactivity, how to customize an application user interface (UI), best practices and workflows for developing shiny apps, and how to deploy apps online via Posit’s hosting service, <a href="https://www.shinyapps.io/">shinyapps.io</a>.</p>
<!-- <br> -->
</section>
<section id="when-is-this-taught" class="level1">
<h1>When is this taught?</h1>
<p>This course began as a humble, 2-hour long workshop in Winter 2022, when I was just beginning to learn Shiny myself. It was expanded into a credit-bearing 2-day long course in Winter 2023, and I’ve revamped / reorganized materials into their own course website for Winter 2024. You can expect that materials will be reviewed and updated at least once annually, around late fall - early winter.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>MEDS</category>
  <category>active-course</category>
  <guid>https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-296-shiny/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:37:20 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-296-shiny/shiny-hex-small.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>EDS 296 - Data science tools for building professional online portfolios</title>
  <link>https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-296-ds-portfolios/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="grid">
<div class="g-col-12 g-col-md-6">
<div class="cell" data-layout-align="center">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-296-ds-portfolios/quarto.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="g-col-12 g-col-md-6">
<div class="cell" data-layout-align="left">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-296-ds-portfolios/github.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" style="width:95.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="center-text">
<p><a href="https://ucsb-meds.github.io/EDS-296-DS-portfolios/" class="btn" target="_blank"><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> course website (no longer maintained)</a></p>
</div>
<!-- [ course catalog](https://bren.ucsb.edu/courses/eds-296-1f){.btn target=_blank} -->
<p><br></p>
<p><strong><em>NOTE: Beginning Fall 2025, course content will be delivered as part of the newly-structured <a href="../../courses/career-dev/index.html">MEDS Career &amp; Professional Development Workshop Series</a>, in collaboration with Bren’s Career Services Team.</em> </strong></p>
<section id="course-description" class="level1">
<h1>Course description</h1>
<p>Having a polished online presence is essential for showcasing your skills, projects, expertise, and (importantly) your personality. Learners, collaborators, and future employers alike will look to your public online profiles to glean information about you and your work. As data scientists, this often means that they’ll head to one of two places: GitHub and / or your personal website. This course is designed to help you both lay the foundation for creating and maintaining these profiles in an organized, informative, and visually-appealing way. Over the next several weeks, you will:</p>
<ul>
<li>build and deploy your personal website using popular data science tools and frameworks</li>
<li>create your first (of many!) data science blog posts</li>
<li>learn about how best to communicate your work to different audiences</li>
<li>understand where and how to document your projects and code</li>
<li>and more!</li>
</ul>
<!-- <br> -->
</section>
<section id="when-is-this-taught" class="level1">
<h1>When is this taught?</h1>
<p>This content has taken a variety of forms since MEDS begain in 2021 – we initially taught website development using the <a href="https://rstudio.github.io/distill/" target="_blank"><code>{distill}</code> package</a> in R (see our original <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1c0SZiVvp32UTJ9sK_yVjI8ou6pVdFRXsY2236tiTA1c/edit?tab=t.0" target="_blank">website develoment</a> &amp; <a href="../../posts/2021-09-21-distill-blogs/index.html" target="_blank">blog</a> workshops).</p>
<p>When <a href="https://quarto.org/" target="_blank">Quarto</a> burst onto the scene in 2022, we revamped this content and delivered lessons as separate, non-credit-bearing workshops:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://ucsb-meds.github.io/creating-quarto-websites/" target="_blank">Creating your personal website using Quarto</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ucsb-meds.github.io/customizing-quarto-websites/#/title-slide" target="_blank">Customizing Quarto websites</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2022-10-24-quarto-blogs/index.html" target="_blank">Adding a blog to your existing Quarto website</a></li>
</ul>
<p>In Fall 2024, we combined these workshops into a full 2-unit course, with an additional focus on GitHub as a professional portfolio. While this course was a lot of fun and seemed to work pretty well, conversations with Bren’s <a href="https://bren.ucsb.edu/career-services" target="_blank">Career Services Team</a> highlighted potential benefits of more consistent messaging and collaboration across all of the MEDS career and professional development teaching efforts. We’ll be offering this content as part of our new MEDS Career &amp; Professional Develoment weekly workshop series beginning in Fall 2025.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>MEDS</category>
  <category>inactive-course</category>
  <guid>https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-296-ds-portfolios/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:37:20 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/eds-296-ds-portfolios/quarto-github.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="80" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>MEDS Career &amp; Professional Development Workshop Series</title>
  <link>https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/career-dev/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="cell" data-layout-align="center">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/career-dev/bren.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" style="width:100.0%" alt="An aerial image overlooking Bren Hall with the ocean and palm trees in the background"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="center-text">
<p><a href="https://ucsb-meds.github.io/career-professional-dev/" class="btn" target="_blank"><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> workshop website</a></p>
</div>
<p><br></p>
<section id="description" class="level1">
<h1>Description</h1>
<p>The MEDS Career &amp; Professional Development Workshop Series is a core component of the Bren School’s Career Development Program for Master of Environmental Data Science (MEDS) students. This series is designed to support your <a href="" target="_blank">career readiness</a> by helping you build the skills, awareness, and confidence you’ll need to launch your career as an environmental data scientist.</p>
<p>Success in environmental data science—and in your career more broadly—requires more than technical expertise. It also takes self-awareness, a clear understanding of your strengths and values, and a personal brand that reflects the impact you want to make. Just as important are polished application materials, strong communication and networking skills, and the ability to interview and negotiate with confidence. A compelling portfolio and professional website will not only help you stand out in today’s job market but also highlight the ways your work contributes to solving real environmental challenges.</p>
<p><strong>Through this workshop series, you will:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Gain an inside look at how employers make hiring decisions by stepping into the role of a hiring committee member</li>
<li>Build tailored resumes and cover letters that effectively market your skills and qualifications</li>
<li>Reflect on your values, strengths, and career goals to create an authentic personal brand</li>
<li>Develop a professional portfolio and website that showcases your skills and impact</li>
<li>Learn effective job search strategies to identify and pursue opportunities that align with your career goals</li>
<li>Strengthen your networking, interviewing, and negotiation skills to navigate the job market with confidence</li>
<li>Explore diverse career paths in environmental data science by building relationships and growing your professional network</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="when-is-this-taught" class="level1">
<h1>When is this taught</h1>
<p>The MEDS Career &amp; Professional Development Workshop Series launches in the 2025–2026 academic year. Programming kicks off during summer bootcamp and expands to weekly workshops throughout the fall quarter. While the schedule for winter and spring is still being finalized, we anticipate continuing to offer workshops during those quarters, though with a reduced schedule to give students the space to focus on their job search.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>MEDS</category>
  <category>active-course</category>
  <guid>https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/career-dev/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:37:20 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://samanthacsik.github.io/courses/career-dev/horst-bren-small.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
